{
  "title": "PBL of Nephrology",
  "questions": [
    {
      "stem": "What is the most common complication in a patient with nephrotic syndrome?",
      "options": [
        "Bleeding tendency",
        "Infection"
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "Which of the following cases is NOT initially indicated for a renal biopsy?",
      "options": [
        "A one-year-old boy with nephrotic syndrome which started at the age of 9 months.",
        "An eight-year-old male patient presenting with nephrotic syndrome and blood pressure persistently above 150/100 mmHg and serum creatinine 1.3mg/dl.",
        "A six-year-old female patient with nephrotic syndrome, no gross hematuria but urine analysis showed RBCs 50-60/HPF.",
        "A ten-year-old girl with nephrotic syndrome, malar rash, and arthritis."
      ],
      "correct": 2
    },
    {
      "stem": "In the treatment of hyperkalemia, which of the following DOES NOT lower the serum potassium level?",
      "options": [
        "IV sodium bicarbonate",
        "IV calcium gluconate",
        "Î²2 agonists",
        "IV glucose and insulin"
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "Which of the following is NOT a nutritional recommendation for patients with Chronic Kidney Disease (CKD)?",
      "options": [
        "Decreased Na intake",
        "K restrictions",
        "Increased phosphate intake",
        "Normal protein intake"
      ],
      "correct": 2
    },
    {
      "stem": "Which of the following supports the diagnosis of glomerular hematuria?",
      "options": [
        "Isomorphic RBCs >90% in urine analysis",
        "RBCs casts in urine analysis",
        "Presence of loin pain",
        "Protein/creatinine ratio 0.15g/g creatinine"
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "In a child with acute pyelonephritis, which of the following is NOT true?",
      "options": [
        "Posterior urethral valve can be a predisposing factor.",
        "Fever is an uncommon feature.",
        "Urine analysis may contain white blood cell casts.",
        "Radio-isotopic renal scan is one of the diagnostic tools."
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "Which of the following findings is not expected in patients with late stages of chronic kidney disease?",
      "options": [
        "Blood gases showing a pH of 7.6",
        "Hemoglobin level of 8 gm%",
        "Serum calcium of 7 mg/dl",
        "Serum K of 6 mEq/L"
      ],
      "correct": 0
    },
    {
      "stem": "What is the mechanism of acute kidney injury in severe dehydration?",
      "options": [
        "Pre-renal AKI",
        "Post-renal AKI",
        "Electrolyte disturbance",
        "Autoimmune mechanism"
      ],
      "correct": 0
    },
    {
      "stem": "Which of the following molecules is NOT freely filtered through the glomerular barrier?",
      "options": [
        "Electrolytes",
        "Glucose",
        "Proteins",
        "Urea"
      ],
      "correct": 2
    },
    {
      "stem": "Which of the following is NOT one of the initial therapies for a first attack of primary nephrotic syndrome?",
      "options": [
        "Cyclosporine",
        "IV Albumin infusion",
        "Oral prednisone",
        "Salt restriction"
      ],
      "correct": 0
    },
    {
      "stem": "Which of the following is a cause of acute kidney injury due to a pre-renal cause?",
      "options": [
        "Bilateral renal stones",
        "Excessive bleeding during an operation",
        "Hemolytic uremic syndrome",
        "Overdose of gentamicin"
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "In a child with acute pyelonephritis, which of the following is not true?",
      "options": [
        "Posterior urethral valve can be a predisposing factor.",
        "Fever is an uncommon feature.",
        "Urine analysis may contain white blood cell casts.",
        "Radio-isotopic renal scan is one of the diagnostic tools."
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "Which of the following supports the diagnosis of glomerular hematuria?",
      "options": [
        "Isomorphic RBCs >90% in urine analysis",
        "RBCs casts in urine analysis",
        "Presence of loin pain",
        "Protein/creatinine ratio 0.15g/g creatinine"
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "A 5-year-old girl presents to the ER with a 2-day history of fever, vomiting, and dysuria. Examination shows suprapubic tenderness. What is the best way to collect a urine sample?",
      "options": [
        "Clean catch",
        "Suprapubic aspirate",
        "Urine bag",
        "Urinary catheter"
      ],
      "correct": 0
    },
    {
      "stem": "A 10-year-old girl presents with lower abdominal pain, dysuria, and gross hematuria for the last 2 days. She has no fever or flank pain. UA shows >100 WBCs, 10-15 RBCs. Which of the following is the likely diagnosis?",
      "options": [
        "Acute Pyelonephritis",
        "Cystitis",
        "Hemoglobinuria",
        "IgA nephropathy"
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "A 3-year-old girl presents with recurrent UTI. What is the most appropriate initial investigation to evaluate her condition?",
      "options": [
        "Abdominal U/S",
        "CT abdomen",
        "Plain x-ray abdomen",
        "VCUG"
      ],
      "correct": 0
    },
    {
      "stem": "Which of the following is wrong about nocturnal enuresis?",
      "options": [
        "ADH rises during sleep",
        "Anticholinergic drugs can be used",
        "Drug therapy is the last therapeutic option",
        "Family history may be present"
      ],
      "correct": 0
    },
    {
      "stem": "The most sensitive investigation for the detection of vesicoureteric reflux (VUR) is:",
      "options": [
        "CT abdomen",
        "IVP",
        "Ultrasonography",
        "VCUG"
      ],
      "correct": 3
    },
    {
      "stem": "A 7-year-old girl presented with burning urination & abdominal pain. She developed bedwetting in the last 5 days after being dry for more than 1 year. Urine was turbid but of normal color. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
      "options": [
        "Acute cystitis",
        "Acute Glomerulonephritis",
        "Acute pyelonephritis",
        "Acute pancreatitis"
      ],
      "correct": 0
    },
    {
      "stem": "A child has suprapubic pain almost every day, with a new onset of nocturnal enuresis and crying during urination. A urine dipstick is positive for WBCs, nitrite, leucocyte esterase, and RBCs. What is the most likely diagnosis?",
      "options": [
        "Acute cystitis",
        "Chronic constipation",
        "Glomerulonephritis",
        "Psychological problem"
      ],
      "correct": 0
    },
    {
      "stem": "Risk factors for UTI include all of the following except:",
      "options": [
        "Male sex",
        "Urinary tract anomaly",
        "Urinary stones",
        "Vesicoureteral reflux (VUR)"
      ],
      "correct": 0
    },
    {
      "stem": "The presence of RBCs casts indicates that the origin of hematuria is:",
      "options": [
        "The glomeruli",
        "The urinary bladder",
        "The renal pelvis",
        "The ureter"
      ],
      "correct": 0
    },
    {
      "stem": "The true statement about nocturnal enuresis is:",
      "options": [
        "It is more common in girls.",
        "It may be the initial presentation of type 1 DM.",
        "It should be investigated by a renal isotopic scan.",
        "It has a worse prognosis than diurnal enuresis."
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "Pyelonephritis commonly presents with:",
      "options": [
        "Dysuria",
        "Fever and rigors",
        "Hypothermia",
        "Prolonged jaundice"
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "Which of the following is true regarding primary nocturnal enuresis?",
      "options": [
        "It's defined as bedwetting after the age of 3 years.",
        "It may be associated with adenoid hypertrophy.",
        "It has a high rate of recurrence and a bad prognosis.",
        "Most children have organic causes."
      ],
      "correct": 1
    },
    {
      "stem": "Regarding nocturnal enuresis, which statement is correct?",
      "options": [
        "Family history is positive in 10% of the cases.",
        "It is more common in females.",
        "It is never caused by an organic cause.",
        "The prognosis is good in the primary type."
      ],
      "correct": 3
    }
  ]
}
